בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף ד. daf dalet.
We pick up two lines from the second line from the top
on ד עמוד א. dalet amud aleph. We had a little number
of statements yesterday relating to the issue of if you don't say
משיב הרוח mashiv haruach or you don't say מוריד הטל morid hatal
or you don't mention the clouds, which we never mention, it's not
a problem because these things never stop, which led to a number
of meteorological statements. A number of them in the name of רבא.
Rava. So now we're going to have a continuance with some statements
of רבא, Rava, which have a loose tie-in and then they'll broaden
a little bit. So let's take a look. Second line from the
top. ואמר רבא, ve-amar Rava, and רבא Rava also says, האי צורבא
מרבנן, hai tzurba merabbanan, a young rabbinic student, says צורבא tzurba means
like a young rabbinic student, דמי לפרצידא, dami le-partzida, is like a
פרצידא, partzida, which is like a little sprout, a tiny little seed
under the ground, דתותי קלא, de-tusei kala, that is under like a
clump of earth that's under the ground, דכיון דנבט נבט. de-keivan de-navat
navat. Once it starts like sprouting forth, it begins to sprout forth.
Like you know this is a person I guess with a lot
of at the beginning of their career, so once things start, you
know, once they start to become successful and growing, then it'll then
you know like its a sprout shoots out of the ground and
it just grows from there. ואמר רבא, ve-amar Rava, and רבא Rava
also said, האי צורבא מרבנן דרתח. hai tzurba merabbanan de-ratach. Now we're
going to talk about young rabbinic students, not with the whole
more agricultural metaphor which we were dealing with, which was the obvious
tie-in, but now we're broadening it a little bit. So if a
young rabbinic student דרתח de-ratach that gets very angry, so you should
be try to be a little bit understanding, seems to be רבא's
Rava point. אורייתא היא דקמרתחא ליה. Oraita hu de-kamratach lei. It's the
Torah in him that's like burning up in him in him and
it might act to cause him to act inappropriately, maybe a little
bit overly passionate. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, הלוא כה דברי
כאש נאם ה'. halo ko devari ka-esh neum Hashem. So are my
words like fire says God. So somebody, you know, is very like
religiously motivated, excited, you know, feels the passion of it, they might
lead them to get angry or to overreact.
ואמר רב אשי, ve-amar Rav Ashi, and says רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
כל תלמיד חכם שאינו קשה כברזל. kol talmid chacham she-eino kasheh ke-barzel.
Now רב אשי Rav Ashi seems to, whereas רבא's Rava statement could
be interpreted a little bit more as explaining and contextualizing, רב אשי
Rav Ashi seems to be like condoning, that any תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham who's not as hard as iron, as strong and as hard
as iron, אינו תלמיד חכם, eino talmid chacham, is not a
תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, וכפטיש יפצץ
סלע. u-kefatish yifotzetz sela. And like a hammer which will shatter a
rock. So maybe, you know, you have to have that single-mindedness and
that sense of conviction, you know, and focus in order to just,
you know, to pursue your Torah studies, you need to be sometimes
a little bit hard, not a pushover. אמר ליה רב אבא לרב
אשי, amar lei Rav Abba le-Rav Ashi, so רב אבא Rav Abba
said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אתון מהתם מתניתו לה, atun me-hatam
matnitu lah, you learn it out from there. אנן מהכא מתנינן לה,
anan me-hacha matninan lah, we learn it out from the following פסוק
pasuk דכתיב, dikhtiv, the verse says, ארץ אשר אבניה ברזל, eretz asher
avaneha barzel, a land whose rocks are iron. אל תקרי אבניה, al
tikrei avaneha, do not read rocks, אלא בוניה, ela boneha,
those that build it. That's, you know, the famous way the חז"ל
Chazal learn the word בוניך, bonayikh, right? רב שלום בוניך אל תקרי
בניך אלא בוניך. rav shalom bonayikh al tikrei banayikh ela bonayikh. You
know, those that like build the world and so on. So they're
as hard as iron. Now again, it's here to clearly it seems
to be more condoning. This is appropriate. Even the association with בוניה
boneha to build, you know like you want your building materials to
be out of iron. So there's some sense here that sometimes, you
know, you gotta be you know strong in this type of religious
pursuit.
Yes, there's there's another
layer or play to that as a famous מדרש Midrash that you
just brought in, that this word בוניה boneha and בוניך bonayikh
build on the שורש להבין, shoresh le-havin,
as they both come to understand it as in like the שורש
רבון? shoresh ravon?
רבון, ravon, right. Yeah that's a good question. I mean we do
all wonder like what is that common דרשה drasha of like בניך
banayikh and בוניך bonayikh and is it builders or is it
like תבונן tivunan understanding? So yeah, thank you for that. Right. Okay,
so so here's again it's sort of saying that it's like sometimes,
you know, you gotta be a little
bit a little bit strong in your in your focus and your
convictions and also if it's a pursuit of truth then in your,
you know, standing up for what's right. אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, but
now we get the counterbalancing, similarly to the way that רבא Rava
seemed more to be contextualizing than than sort of praising or condoning,
here we move to a type of a praising approach but now
we're still going to balance it. So said רבינא, Ravina, אפילו הכי,
afilu hakhi, even if all that is true. מיבעי ליה לאיניש למיילף
נפשיה בניחותא. Miba'ei lei le'inish lemeilef nafshiah benichusa. You have to teach
yourself how to deal pleasantly with people. Like it could very be
nice that you know you're strong and you have your convictions, but
learn teach yourself how to deal pleasantly. שנאמר Shenemar as the verse
says והסר כעס מלבך Vehaser kaas milibecha remove anger from your heart.
So that a little bit seems to be going back to רבא
Rava who speaks about רתחא ליה Ritcha lei anger like you know,
but here it's but it's also put here to juxtapose the statement
of רב אשי. Rav Ashi. So it's all very nice that passion
and conviction you know and strength of character, but there's also a
way that you interact you know with other people and you learn
how to do that properly. Sort of reminds me of that statement
by what's his name, but I the statement is quoted in so
many different ways by רבי ישראל סלנטר. Rabbi Yisrael Salanter. What is
it? That any rabbi people know this line? What is it? Any
rabbi who's something like something like any rabbi who you know who
doesn't stand up to his congregation isn't a man but any rabbi
who's congregation whatever isn't a מענטש. mensch. I don't know. I guess
some type of I there's some type of good statement like that
that I it is, but I forget the exact line. Anyway, but
it's about the idea of on the one hand you have to
you know have you know not be a pushover and you're standing
for תורה Torah and you're standing for truth and you have that
conviction at the other hand you have to be able to deal
with you know interact with people in a מענטשליך menschlich way. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara gets back to it's still in
an אגדתא agadata mode but we'll circle back to our theme here.
So let's take a look. אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan שלושה שאלו שלא
כהוגן, Shlosha sha'alu shelo ke'hogen, three asked inappropriately. ולשניים השיבוהו U'lishnayim heshivuhu
or השיבום heshivum כהוגן, ke'hogen, two were responded even though their request
was inappropriate and could have led to something disastrous as we'll see,
they got the right response that or they got the response that
was appropriate. ולאחד השיבוהו שלא כהוגן, U'le'echad heshivuhu shelo ke'hogen, one person
the response was inappropriate corresponding to the way it was requested. ואלו
הן, Ve'elu hen, these are the three: אליעזר עבד אברהם, Eliezer eved
Avraham, אליעזר Eliezer the the servant of אברהם. Avraham. The reason he's
called עבד אברהם Eved Avraham here is because it's talking about the
story with רבקה Rivka where he's never identified in the תורה Torah
as אליעזר, Eliezer, just as עבד אברהם, Eved Avraham, but חז"ל Chazal
identify him as אליעזר. Eliezer. What?
שלא כהוגן? Shelo ke'hogen?
Well we will see. ושאול בן קיש Ve'Shaul ben Kish and שאול,
Shaul, ויפתח הגלעדי Veyiftach ha'Giladi and יפתח. Yiftach. אליעזר עבד אברהם דכתיב
Eliezer eved Avraham de'chtiv אליעזר Eliezer the servant of אברהם Avraham as
it says והיה הנערה אשר אומר אליה הטי נא כדך ואשתה ואמרה
שתה וגם גמליך אשקה אותה הוכחת לעבדך ליצחק. Vehaya hana'ara asher omar
eleiha hati na kadeich ve'eshte ve'amra shetei ve'gam gemalecha ashke osa hochechta
le'avdecha le'Yitzchak. Right, that will be the one you've chosen for יצחק.
Yitzchak. So whoever passes the test he said that'll be the one.
יכול אפילו חיגרת אפילו סומא? Yachol afilu chigeres afilu suma? Maybe even
if she would be lame even if she'd be blind? Somebody that
wouldn't be appropriate for יצחק? Yitzchak? We're not going to get into
here again the whole problem with you know approaching people with disabilities
but okay. Maybe somebody could pass the test and not be appropriate
for for
other reasons, okay.
So anyway רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot says but it doesn't end,
in order to pass the test he first have to say to
her give me the drink. So why can't he check these things
out before he says to her? Well, he says maybe it's not
an obvious disability and so on you know maybe maybe maybe it's
hidden. But anyway, we won't also deal again with the I think
a deeper problem here about about categorizing people with disabilities. Anyway, השיבוהו
כהוגן, Heshivuhu ke'hogen, he got the woman he was looking for. ונזדמנה
לו רבקה Venizdamna lo Rivka and exactly the right woman chanced upon
him. So it could have been he passed the test and still
not be the right person and nevertheless ברוך השם Baruch Hashem it
worked out. שאול בן קיש דכתיב Shaul ben Kish de'chtiv שאול בן
קיש Shaul ben Kish as it says והיה האיש אשר יכנו יעשרנו
המלך עושר גדול ואת בתו יתן לו. Vehaya ha'ish asher yakenu ya'asrenu
ha'melech osher gadol ve'es bito yiten lo. This is by גלית Golyas
by right גוליית, Goliath, he says the that Saul said that whoever
smites him the king will enrich with great wealth and give him
his daughter to as a wife. יכול אפילו עבד אפילו ממזר? Yachol
afilu eved afilu mamzer? What, anybody who passes the test? Even a
slave? Even a ממזר? mamzer? So I mean he it's one thing
to give him wealth, but you marry off your daughter to him?
So השיבוהו כהוגן, Heshivuhu ke'hogen, nevertheless even though he wasn't careful in
how he phrased it and it could have been a bad result,
he got exactly the appropriate result. ונזדמן לו דוד Venizdamen lo David
and דוד David was the one. Not that שאול Shaul was so
happy with דוד David in the future, but okay, at least at
least initially at least it was the right of all the possible
you know sort of results that was the best. יפתח הגלעדי Yiftach
ha'Giladi now יפתח, Yiftach, this is the most fascinating one דכתיב de'chtiv
והיה היוצא אשר יצא מדלתי ביתי, Vehaya hayotze asher yetzei mi'daltei beisi,
it will be the thing that comes out of my door first
when I come back from the war, I will offer it as
a sacrifice to God. So he said whatever comes out of my
door. So it says יכול אפילו דבר טמא? Yachol afilu davar tamei?
Maybe even and he wasn't careful, maybe it would have even referred
to let's say a non-kosher thing like a pig. Now of course
it's quite funny because it could have said maybe even if it's
a person which is exactly what happened. But maybe it means that
even if he wasn't even thinking about that possibility, he should have
at least been thinking about the possibility. it could be a non-kosher
animal. השיבו שלא כהוגן Heishivu shelo kehogen and he got what was
sort of his comeuppance there. It didn't work out. Yeah, we don't
know. It's fascinating. It doesn't it doesn't reflect on like why was
that, you know, that that God allowed the first two to work
out well and this one not. שנאמר Shene'emar as the verse says,
I'm sorry, השיבו שלא כהוגן Heishivu shelo kehogen ויזדמן לו בתו ve-nizdamen
lo bito and it was his daughter that walked out of the
door. והיינו דקאמר להו נביא לישראל Ve-hainu d'ka'amar lehu navi l'Yisrael and
this is what the נביא navi says to ישראל Yisrael in ירמיהו,
Yirmeyahu, הצרי אין בגלעד אם רופא אין שם Hatzori ein b'Gilad im
rofe ein sham is there no myrrh in Gilead is there no
healing there? So גלעד Gilad is יפתח הגלעדי Yiftach HaGiladi and the
נביא navi is bemoaning the fact that obviously because you know the
problem with those פסוקים psukim are that the problem with the story
of יפתח Yiftach is not just that יפתח Yiftach did what he
did. I mean okay so it was one person, you don't know
you know maybe it was obviously considered a heinous act. But if
you read the story there's nothing in the story of יפתח Yiftach
other than the fact that it's like a tragedy that this girl
has to you know die at a young age, there's nothing in
the way the נביא navi tells the story of יפתח Yiftach that
makes it sound like this thing is like horrific from a religious
standpoint, right? It was just terrible that this young girl had to
like you know she gathered all her friends around she mourned over
the fact that you know she'll die a virgin but there's nothing
there that makes it seem like this thing is like fundamentally you
know religiously abhorrent. So the גמרא Gemara here is trying to express
the idea it's a funny thing. On the one hand he sort
of got what was coming to him but you know part of
the message is like yeah but we see in other stories that
God sort of could have you know had a way of making
things work out. God here allowed it or intentionally made it work
out bad which seems to even more heighten the problem that this
is not being sort of condemned. And therefore now we're going to
quote פסוקים psukim to balance that that says that God was very
like that this was unacceptable. So the first פסוק pasuk that we're
quoting you know is that there was no healing, that this was
a terrible thing you know and it was and there was no
way to heal you know this problem. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
that it alludes to the fact that the מדרש Midrash that says
that פינחס Pinchas was around at that time and he could have
gone to פינחס Pinchas to be מתיר הנדר matir the neder and
he didn't, and פינחס Pinchas didn't go to him. פינחס Pinchas said
let him come to me, and יפתח Yiftach said let פינחס Pinchas
come to me. And therefore like they both sort of were punished
for not trying to solve the problem and be מתיר הנדר matir
the neder and that's also this הצרי אין בגלעד Hatzori ein b'Gilad
like why is nobody solving this problem? But again what the גמרא
Gemara is trying to do and it is very funny because like
the first thing is like oh so God wanted this to happen.
So God was all all like controlling this you know by certainly
contrasting it to the other two stories and then at the same
time saying that this was completely unacceptable which is even more heightened
in the next פסוק. pasuk. So let's just read the next פסוק
pasuk and it says give me a second and it says וכתיב
U-chtiv and the other verse says right in ירמיהו Yirmeyahu referring to
the fact that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael would offer up their
children like you know in these fire offerings, this right of child
sacrifice, and the verse there says אשר לא צויתי ולא דברתי ולא
עלתה על לבי Asher lo tziviti v'lo dibarti v'lo alta al libi
that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael would do these you know child sacrifices
I think to the מולך Moloch is the context or to גיא
בן הננום, Gei Ben Hinnom, במות הבעל Bamotei Baal right, לשרוף
את בניהם
lisrof
et
bnehem thank you okay I think so. And it says that I
did not command and I never spoke and it never occurred to
me. This is something that I never wanted, child sacrifice. So the
גמרא Gemara here says in a way this is like a very
you know the גמרא Gemara sort of here like based on this
verse pulls together stories which don't which sort of are a little
problematic, make it a little make you a little bit question how
much has child sacrifice been completely eradicated and completely something God does
not want? So let's take a look. So it says אשר לא
צויתי Asher lo tziviti that I never commanded זה בנו של מישע
מלך מואב. zeh bno shel Mesha melech Moav.
This is the son of מישע Mesha the king of מואב Moav
שנאמר shene'emar the verse says ויקח את בנו הבכור אשר ימלך תחתיו
ויעלהו עלה. va-yikach et bno habechor asher yimloch tachtav va-ya-alehu olah. So
now this is about a non-Jew, fine, but if you know the
story there they're going to war against ישראל Yisrael and it looks
like מואב Moav is about to be destroyed and he takes his
son which would have been his the king underneath him and he
brings him up as a sacrifice and then the next thing is
that that you know that they that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael sort
of the war breaks off, they don't succeed, they don't vanquish him.
So it seems like his sacrifice was accepted because after he offers
up his son as a sacrifice he actually they escape defeat. So
it had a positive effect or at least you know at least
if you sort of you know what's the point? Juxtaposition is not
causality right just because one thing follows the other doesn't mean that
it was causal, but the תורה Torah never said like God answered
him. But after he offers up his son they don't get defeated
like it looked like they were about to suffer imminent defeat. So
it says oh but I never wanted that. You know I wasn't
asking for that, I didn't want that, that's not what that was
about. Okay, ולא דברתי V'lo dibarti I never spoke it, זה יפתח.
zeh Yiftach. I never told יפתח Yiftach to do it, it was
him he did
it.
It never even occurred to me, זה יצחק בן אברהם, zeh Yitzchak
ben Avraham, that was יצחק. Yitzchak. I said העלהו לעולה, ha'alehu l'olah,
but it never really occurred to me that that would really be
how it would be played out, I just did it as a
test or I did it because I meant bring him up, but
I didn't mean it like רש״י, Rashi, the famous רש״י Rashi quotes
the מדרש, Midrash, I didn't literally mean sacrifice him, and okay, maybe
it's probably also a play on the word
עלתה alta and
תעלהו לעולה, ta'alehu l'olah, although עלתה alta also occurs by what do
you call it? By מישע Mesha King of מואב. Moab. So here
the גמרא Gemara and this actually is interesting because some scholars actually
do raise this question which is, how much was the idea or
the impetus for child sacrifice really completely eradicated?
I mean if you just think about some of the מדרשים Midrashim
by the case of the עקידה, Akedah, first of all the עקידה
Akedah presents of course for a lot
of very deep religious issues nowadays in the sense of following a
religious mandate
even if it's unethical, calls for murder, and so on especially in
the day now things we deal with with religious fundamentalism, which starts
all the way the earliest sort of problematizing of that with the
עקידה Akedah or the most famous goes back to Kierkegaard,
but that's not necessarily how the עקידה Akedah was looked at traditionally.
The עקידה Akedah traditionally was not looked at as the challenge of
do you listen to God against your sense of morality and right
and wrong like if you think about what we say in the
liturgy, in the liturgy we say, כשם שכבש אברהם אבינו את רחמיו
לעשות רצונך בלבב שלם כן יכבשו רחמיך, k'shem she'kavash Avraham Avinu et
rachamav la'asot retzoncha b'levav shalem kein yichbeshu rachamecha,
אברהם Avraham was willing to overcome his compassion to give what is
most dear to him to do your will, you God should be
able to overcome your anger against us. So it wasn't that he
overcame his sense of right and wrong, but he gave over what
was most dear to him. So it's not problematized as a fundamental
issue of morality
and murder, it's just doing what is most dear. So and that
was the test and if you think about the רש״י Rashi quoting
the מדרש, Midrash, I mean it's really a מדרש בראשית רבה, Midrash
Bereishit Rabbah, but where it says when it says אברהם Avraham took
the ram and he and ויעלהו לעולה תחת בנו, v'ya'alehu l'olah tachat
b'no, so what
does תחת בנו tachat b'no mean? It means as he was שוחט
shechting the ram he said let this be like I'm שוחט shechting
יצחק, Yitzchak, and as he was sprinkling the blood he says let
this be like the blood of יצחק. Yitzchak. I mean it's very
graphic, but what it's basically saying to us is that that impetus
for child sacrifice doesn't just go away and even if God is
saying give a substitute, it doesn't mean that it gets eradicated and
there's still that sense in some people's minds. Somebody told me this
could only be men, like women would never think this way, a
mother would never think this
way, but there's this sense of give what's most dear, you give
your first son. Did you see the movie נח? Noah? נח, Noah,
נח, Noah, נח, Noah, so anyway I won't ruin it for you,
but at the end you have a scene just like that, the
father or the grandfather like he thinks God wants my son, the
mother will never think that way. But anyway, so what this is
doing is it's actually pointing out that there are cases in the
תנ״ך Tanakh where it seems like people are acting on this and
it doesn't seem to be completely
condemned. The story of יפתח, Yiftach, the story of מישע מלך מואב,
Mesha Melech Moav, which again brings God and בני ישראל B'nei Yisrael
into that equation. So the גמרא Gemara here is like based on
the פסוק pasuk in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu and it seems to be that
is part of ירמיהו's Yirmiyahu rhetoric is insisting don't read those stories
that way. These stories should not be read that there would ever
be a hint that God would want this and that was completely
something that never God had desired. And the גמרא Gemara though is
dealing with that tension here. So on the one hand, השיבו שלא
כהוגן, heshivo shelo k'hogen, and
he could have God could have made something else occur but he
made the daughter be the one or God allowed for the daughter
to be the one, and on the other hand don't interpret this
to mean that this is something that God ever wanted. God would
never want this, this was completely unexpected. So let's just read a
little more and take the question. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר
רב
ברכיה, Amar Rav Brachia, אף כנסת ישראל שאלה שלא כהוגן, af Knesset
Yisrael sha'alah shelo k'hogen, even the כנסת ישראל Knesset Yisrael asked
inappropriately, והקדוש ברוך הוא השיבה כהוגן, v'ha'Kadosh Baruch Hu heshivah k'hogen, and
this will just be the tie-in to our מסכת, masechet, and God
responded though appropriately, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, as it says, ונדעה נרדפה לדעת את
ה׳, v'neid'ah nird'fah lada'at et Hashem, let us know and to run
to know God, כשחר נכון מוצאו, k'shachar nachon motza'o, like the morning
or like the sun which is trustworthy its rising of the sun,
ויבוא כגשם לנו, v'yavo k'geshem lanu, and it will come down like
rain to us. So אמר לה הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar lah ha'Kadosh
Baruch Hu, so God said to the children of ישראל, Yisrael, בתי,
biti, my daughter, את שואלת דבר שפעמים מתבקש ופעמים אינו מתבקש? at
sho'elet davar she'p'amim mitbikes v'p'amim eino mitbikes? You're asking for something that
sometimes is desirable and sometimes is not desirable, like we've been learning,
rain in the wrong time is a bad thing, it's a קללה.
klalah. So you want it to be like rain? Rain isn't always
desirable. אבל אני אהיה לך דבר המתבקש לעולם, aval ani eheyeh lach
davar ha'mitbikes l'olam, I will be for you something that is always
desirable. שנאמר אהיה כטל לישראל. Shene'emar ehyeh k'tal l'Yisrael. I'll be like
the dew. So as we were learning yesterday, the dew is always
present and, you know, always good, although it's just before a טל
tal of ברכה brachah and טל tal not of ברכה, brachah, but
anyway, and therefore that is God's response. Okay,
to finish up this point, ועוד שאלה שלא כהוגן v'od she'alah shelo
khahogen one final request that was inappropriate. אמר לפניו ריבונו של עולם
Amar lefanav Ribbono shel Olam Master of the Universe, שימני כחותם על
לבך כחותם על זרועך Simeini chachosem al libecha kachosem al zeroecha make
me like a seal on your heart, like a seal on your
arm. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu God
said, בתי, Biti, you ask for something שפעמים נראה פעמים אינו נראה
shepeamim nireh peamim eino nireh that sometimes is visible, sometimes is not
visible. You don't, things that are on your arm, you know, could
be covered up with your clothes, with your sleeves. אבל אני אעשה
לך דבר שנראה לעולם Aval ani eeseh lach davar shenireh leolam I
will be for you something that is always seen, שנאמר הן על
כפיים חקתיך shene'emar hen al kapayim chakotich behold, I have carved you
onto my, you know, very palms, something that is always visible. So
I just want to say by the way, besides the idea here
of the issue of טל tal versus גשם, geshem, the other important
theme that this is bringing up, which is a major major theme
of this מסכת, masechet, is rain as a metaphor, maybe even better
to say
as an expression of God's closeness to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Part
of the whole issue of is it raining, is it not raining,
is not just we need the rain for the crops, but are
we finding favor with God or not finding favor with God? If
it's not raining, that means that God is distant from us. And
the rain comes down from the heaven. It's the most sort of,
you know, most physical thing that expresses, if you think about it,
it's almost like the reverse of sacrifices. Right? The sacrifices you make
a fire and it goes up to heaven, and the rain, you
know, is the life-giving thing that comes down from heaven, and it's
that powerful not only even a symbol, you know, but in a
sense a powerful, like, you know, manifestation of God's desiring and connecting
to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So here that theme is really brought
up in this sense of be like rain, be like dew, expressing
that relationship between God and בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Okay, there were
a few questions. Charlie?
Yeah, יפתח Yiftach is not the only
bad
event in ספר שופטים Sefer Shoftim that seems to not get condemned,
but later on the נביאים Neviim are more seem to be more
likely to condemn the actions of some of the bad
kings, the
idolatry, so
there's
a question why is ספר שופטים Sefer Shoftim so much just plain
סתם?
stam? Why does it give him a pass as much as there?
Yeah, I agree. So that's the question. And again, the question is
exactly quoting the פסוק pasuk in ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. Is it that maybe
the thing was not seen as horrific
earlier on? So, right, I mean that's the question. When God says
don't bring יצחק, Yitzchak, is God saying because child sacrifice is completely
horrific and I never want it? Or is God just saying I'm
not asking that from you, but it's not like the thing itself
is incomprehensible? So obviously we would like to think the former, but
on the other
hand, the subject of child sacrifice, current Biblical Archaeology Review has an
article on child sacrifice.
Specifically on Carthage, which was a Phoenician
Canaanite colony.
And the conclusion is, yeah, they did it.
And it was not that uncommon.
I was going to say, it's
one thing
to point out by the other פסוקים pesukim that God didn't say
to יפתח Yiftach don't sacrifice your daughter, you didn't say to מישע
Meisha king of מואב Moav when he sacrificed his son, okay, then
you can sort of get away with it that God didn't want
it.
Well that I think is why it leaves the אשר לא עלתה
על לבי asher lo altah al libi for יצחק. Yitzchak. Because by
יצחק Yitzchak it was צויתי tziviti and it was דברתי, dibarti, it
just wasn't עלתה על לבי. altah al libi. Otherwise I could say
yeah I said it, but I didn't mean it. I said it
but I didn't mean it. Okay, so anyway that ends that discussion,
an aggadic end to the whole issue about תן טל ומטר ten
tal umatar and excuse me, about
מוריד הטל, morid hatal, not saying it, and if he even drops
off the משיב הרוח mashiv haruach that doesn't cease. I should just
mention להלכה lehalachah that, okay, so it says you don't have to
say מוריד הטל morid hatal at any time. In theory you could
say it at all times. You could say in the winter and
fall מוריד הטל, morid hatal, משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם mashiv haruach umorid
hagashem if you want to. And you could say it during the
summer and the spring מוריד הטל. morid hatal. But it says you
don't have to. So תוספות Tosafot quotes a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says
that if you say מוריד הטל morid hatal instead and you know,
let's say you say it all the time, and let's say you
say it in the summer but then you kept on saying it
in the rainy season as well and you forgot to say משיב
הרוח ומוריד הגשם, mashiv haruach umorid hagashem, excuse me, that you don't
have to go back. Because, and therefore it leads to a position
in תוספות, Tosafot, which is not the position of the רמ"א Rema
and most אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, but it is I believe the position of
ספרדים, Sefardim, correct me Dov if I'm wrong, and I believe other
certain strands of אשכנזי Ashkenazi נוסח, nusach, which is that you say
מוריד הטל morid hatal in the summer and in the spring, and
therefore the side benefit of it, it never says it's bad
to
say. you'll mention another שבח shevach of הקדוש ברוך הוא, HaKadosh Baruch
Hu, why is that bad? No problem. And the other benefit of
it is is that if you forget to say משיב הרוח Mashiv
HaRuach once ומוריד הגשם uMorid HaGeshem specifically מוריד הגשם Morid HaGeshem once
it becomes like after סוכות Succos and you just say what you've
been used to saying which is מוריד הטל Morid HaTal then you
don't have to go back. So it's perfect. You don't have to
"Oh, did I remember? Did I not remember?" A ספק safek first
30 days, I go back afterwards, I don't go back? If you
won't you'll never have to go back because at worst case is
you said מוריד הטל. Morid HaTal. But by the way it doesn't
mean you'll never go back because there could still be a problem
the other half of the year when you're supposed to stop saying
מוריד הגשם, Morid HaGeshem, right, and it becomes actually you know the
post-פסח Pesach period and you're supposed and then if you do continue
to say מוריד הגשם Morid HaGeshem when you're not supposed to say
it, that we learned also that's the whole idea of rain in
the wrong time is a קללה klalah was a סימן קללה. siman
klalah. So but at least for half the year you don't have
to worry because for half the year either you said משיב הרוח
ומוריד הגשם Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem like you should have or you
said מוריד הטל Morid HaTal and either way you're safe. So that
was that's my מנהג minhag as well like even though not as
much my family מנהג, minhag, I figure like you know there's nothing
no downside and the only thing it can do is help you
half the year not have to worry about going back. The interesting
thing to say about this though is is this and this is
like the flip of the idea in תוספות Tosafos that came up
with if you forgot מוריד הגשם Morid HaGeshem the תוספות Tosafos says
you can say it in שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefila, as I said
yesterday we don't פסקן pasken that way, but that deals with the
issue of משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem being like
an introduction to בקשה, bakasha, so in order not just an appropriate
שבח shevach in that location in שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. And if
you see it as an introduction to בקשה bakasha you could say
it in שומע תפילה Shomea Tefila if you missed it in you
know מחיה מתים. Mechayei Meisim. We again we don't פסקן pasken that
way but that's one way of looking at it. So the flip
thing to have to be asked about מוריד הטל. Morid HaTal. How
does מוריד הטל Morid HaTal get you out of
מוריד הגשם? Morid HaGeshem? You need rain so you need to be
saying גשם. geshem. טל tal never ceases. So why does saying מוריד
הטל Morid HaTal get you out of the obligation of saying מוריד
הגשם? Morid HaGeshem? So if you think that משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem is all about a precursor to asking for
rain then there's no reason מוריד הטל Morid HaTal should get you
out of it because it's not about rain. But if משיב הרוח
ומוריד הגשם Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem is about an obligation to just
sort of acknowledge you know God's power and the fact that God
brings rain as one of the שבחים shvachim of God, so מוריד
הטל Morid HaTal is in the same category, it's recognizing God's power
over the water cycle, over you know the meteorological functions and so
on, things that God does that help bring you know sustenance to
the world. So it's not about a בקשה bakasha for rain, it's
just about a שבח. shevach. So מוריד הטל Morid HaTal could be
seen as a type of a substitute. So that those two questions:
is מוריד הטל Morid HaTal a substitute or an acceptable בדיעבד bedieved
and can you say משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach בדיעבד bedieved in שומע
תפילה Shomea Tefila get to the heart of the question which we're
about to resume which is the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua to some degree which is to what
degree is משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem really just
a precursor to בקשה? bakasha? Okay yeah some questions then and then
we'll move on.
Yeah? I believe אשכנזים Ashkenazim in ישראל Yisrael universally say מוריד הטל.
Morid HaTal. Why?
Could be. I think that's מנהג גר״א. minhag Gra. גר״א Gra said
yeah yeah yeah. I was just gonna say
the other thing is you only get טל tal when it's been
cool enough to get dew when it's you know 80-90 degrees you
know?
Because then it doesn't condense it just all evaporates. Right right.
So on some level right it's still a sign that you're you
know hopefully things your crops are not gonna are not gonna overheat
and burn and so on. It's giving them something positive still since
they grow. Good point.
Yep.
I wanted to clarify. Is it you're saying the only reason why
מוריד הטל Morid HaTal is said is to be safe
the other half of the year? That's not the only reason. I
mean the גמרא Gemara sort of doesn't give a heavy weight to
say it or not say it. It says if you don't say
it it's okay, never really says you're supposed it a little bit
alludes to the idea that maybe you're supposed to say it but
never really makes that point either. So no I said like okay
so first of all say it, it's a positive, the גמרא Gemara
you know certainly never says it's a bad thing to say it,
if anything it's a positive thing to say it because it's another
שבח shevach of הקדוש ברוך הוא. HaKadosh Baruch Hu. But you know
it has a real benefit in terms of this other thing. But
I'm not saying it's the only reason. Okay so let's now move
on. אין שואלין את הגשמים. Ein shoalin es hageshamim. So that's a
good a good segue into this discussion which we're going to again
visit the relationship of מזכירין mazkirin and שואלין. shoalin. So the משנה
Mishnah opens with the case of mentioning משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. Mashiv
HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem. Then it goes there's a lot of back and
forth referred between mentioning and asking, מזכירין ושואלין מזכירין שואלין. mazkirin v'shoalin
mazkirin shoalin. So we had had the debate about when do you
say it. Now we have this one line in the משנה Mishnah
which is אין שואלין את הגשמים אלא סמוך לגשמים. ein shoalin es
hageshamim ela samuch lageshamim. Right? אין שואלין Ein shoalin you only ask
for rain ותן טל ומטר לברכה, v'sein tal u'matar l'vracha,
yeah yeah yeah I'm just looking for the right, אלא סמוך לגשמים
ela samuch lageshamim near the time of the rain. And that's not
so clear what the time of the rain is. Now if you
look at take a peek ahead at the next not the actual
next משנה, Mishnah, well it's a bit ahead, but let me tell
you where it is, the משנה Mishnah on דף י׳ עמוד א׳,
daf yud amud aleph, no not that one, because that tells י׳
עמוד א׳ yud amud aleph it says
right.
So when do you ask? Three of מרחשון Marcheshvan or seven of
מרחשון? Marcheshvan? So that seems to be the clarification of what סמוך
לגשמים samuch lagishomim means. Although you start saying משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem at, you know, at latest after סוכות Sukkot
is over, right, שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, that's when you start saying
it, whole debate whether all of סוכות Sukkot or at the end
of סוכות, Sukkot, but the actual asking for it, that you wait
till it's much more the fully appropriate time till it's the third
or seventh of מרחשון. Marcheshvan. That's presumably how the משנה Mishna reads.
But the גמרא Gemara is not going to necessarily assume that. So
let's take a look. אין שואלין אלא סמוך לגשמים. Ein sho'alin ela
samuch legishomim. סברוה, savruha, we assumed, שאלה והזכרה חד מילתא היא. she'eilah
v'hazkarah chad miltah hi. So the גמרא Gemara says fascinatingly, although רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer explicitly says not this way, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says, no, I'm talking about להזכיר, l'hazkir, not לשאול. lish'ol. The גמרא
Gemara is saying we're assuming that maybe within רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
since רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua doesn't distinguish, you know, doesn't buy into
saying משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach not at the, you know, before you
want it. רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua whole point is you don't say
משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach until you really want the rain, until it
really will be good. So maybe according to him, those two times
are exactly the same, there's no gap between משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach
and ותן טל ומטר. v'tein tal u-matar. שאלה והזכרה she'eilah v'hazkarah occur
at the same time, according at least according to רבי יהושע. Rabbi
Yehoshua. That's what we're assuming. So מאן תנא? man tanna? So who
is this תנא tanna that says that, that you, that you start
asking for it right, you know, when it's the right, when it's
the time of rain? אמר רבא, amar Rava, רבי יהושע היא, Rabbi
Yehoshua hi, דאמר משעת הנחתו. d'amar mish'at hanachaso. It's רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua that says when you start asking for it after you put
down the לולב, lulav, which presumably means שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, and
now the גמרא's Gemara assuming that not only does he say that
you start saying משיב הרוח, Mashiv HaRuach, but you start saying ותן
טל ומטר. v'tein tal u-matar. I mean, don't say it on שמיני
עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, but fine, you'll start saying it the next day.
Okay, that, that, and that those are exactly the same time. אותיביה
אביי, oseivieh Abaye, אביי Abaye said no. אפילו תימא רבי אליעזר, afilu
teima Rabbi Eliezer, even רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, שאלה לחוד והזכרה לחוד,
she'eilah l'chud v'hazkarah l'chud, which is what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said
in the משנה, Mishna, right? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer could agree that
you ask for it later, you know, he just says that mentioning
it comes earlier. So again, the assumption here that you, that you
ask for it, you know, when it's closer to the time that
you want, does not necessarily mean that you wait to mention it,
the mentioning could begin earlier. ואיכא דאמרי, v'ika d'amri, some say, לימא
רבי יהושע היא דאמר משעת הנחתו. leima Rabbi Yehoshua hi d'amar mish'at
hanachaso. So that it started more with like a question, not a
statement. Maybe this idea that you say, you know, that you start
asking ותן טל ומטר, v'tein tal u-matar, maybe that's only רבי אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer? Because assumingly that would mean not only do you start
saying ותן טל ומטר v'tein tal u-matar later, but you start saying
משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach later, so that would only be a רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua idea that says משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach comes later.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא amar Rava no, אפילו תימא
רבי אליעזר, afilu teima Rabbi Eliezer, could even be רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, שאלה לחוד והזכרה לחוד. she'eilah l'chud v'hazkarah l'chud. You could be
that you ask for it later, but you mention it earlier. Again,
seems to be like very obvious that that's what's going on in
the משנה, Mishna, but it's raising the question that while רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says that explicitly, that I'm okay saying משיב הרוח Mashiv
HaRuach during סוכות Sukkot before you say, before you start asking, is
that true according to רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? Is it possible since
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says you don't say משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach
until you, it's really you would want the rain to happen, and
that's our idea that משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach is a precursor to
ותן טל ומטר, v'tein tal u-matar, maybe he doesn't have a gap
of time at all between those two, and maybe he would actually
say that you start saying both of them as soon as סוכות
Sukkot is out. And we're going to continue with that possibility right
here. Let's take a look. רבי יהודה אומר עובר לפני התיבה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer oveir lifnei hateivah. The one who, if you begin the
דאווענינג, davening, the בעל שחרית Baal Shacharit of שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret,
does not say it, and the בעל מוסף Baal Musaf says משיב
הרוח. Mashiv HaRuach. רמינהי, raminhi, I'll ask you on this. עד מתי
שואלין את הגשמים, ad mosai sho'alin et hageshamim, until when do you
ask for it? And the, at the opposite end, the בעל שחרית
Baal Shacharit for, for the first day of פסח Pesach says it,
and the בעל מוסף Baal Musaf does not say it. So until
you, but you say it until the beginning of פסח. Pesach. So
we've got a משנה, Mishna, the next משנה Mishna coming up, and
this is the משנה ה', Mishna hey, not when you begin, but
when you end. עד מתי שואלין את הגשמים, ad mosai sho'alin et
hageshamim, until when do you ask for the rain? רבי יהודה אומר
עד שיעבור הפסח, Rabbi Yehuda omer ad she-ya'avor haPesach, until פסח Pesach
is done, until פסח Pesach is over. רבי מאיר אומר עד שיעבור
ניסן, Rabbi Meir omer ad she-ya'avor Nissan, until all of ניסן Nissan
is over. So we'll put aside רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir for now,
but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda on the one hand says you say
it until the first day of פסח, Pesach, you switch over at
מוסף, Musaf, and in the next משנה Mishna he says you say
it throughout פסח, Pesach, until פסח Pesach is passed over, excuse the
pun. Okay, anyway, so אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן לשאול כאן להזכיר. kan lish'ol kan
lehazkir.
Okay, so it says ah, because our משנה, Mishna, now again we're
getting to this question of do these things overlap or not. Our
משנה Mishna has him say you stop saying משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
Mashiv HaRuach uMorid HaGeshem on the first day of פסח. Pesach. But
he's saying... Fine, that's when you stop saying משיב הרוח, Mashiv Haruach,
but you keep on asking for it and saying תן טל ומטר
לברכה Ten Tal uMatar livracha throughout all of פסח, Pesach, which is
like bizarre, right? Until now we've said you can mention it before,
but you know you're
asking, presumably as long as you're asking, you're also mentioning, right? The
mentioning could come by. But why would the mentioning stop and you
still be a period of asking? If you're still asking for rain,
you should still be saying משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. Mashiv Haruach uMorid
Hageshem. But that's what it thinks to resolve. It would technically resolve
the משניות. Mishnayot. Our משנה Mishnah is talking about mentioning. The next
משנה Mishnah talking about asking. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so
let's see, כאן לשאול כאן להזכיר. kan lish'ol kan lehazkir. מי ששואל
ואזיל, mi shesho'el ve'azil, you keep on asking תן טל ומטר לברכה
Ten Tal uMatar livracha through פסח, Pesach, at least you say it
on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. להזכיר, lehazkir, to say משיב הרוח, Mashiv
Haruach, that you switch over on the first day. ביום טוב הראשון
פוסק, beyom tov harishon posek, you stop on the first day. So
אמר עולא, amar Ula, so עולא Ula said, הא דרב חסדא, ha
deRav Chisda, that statement of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, to think you
would not say משיב הרוח Mashiv Haruach while you're asking for rain,
קשיא כחומץ לשיניים וכעשן לעיניים, kashya kechometz lashinayim uche'ashan la'einayim, quoting a
פסוק pasuk from משלי, Mishlei,
like vinegar to the teeth and smoke to the eyes, like that
thing is like so hard to make sense, it's like
it's the opposite. ומה במקום שאינו שואל מזכיר, uma bimkom she'eino sho'el
mazkir,
before it's even the time to begin asking, you mention,
but you start mentioning according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you mention
it the beginning of סוכות, Sukkot, according to even according to רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua although we're sort of a little bit have some
question about that but you mention from, you know, שמיני עצרת Shemini
Atzeret until מרחשון, Marcheshvan, you're mentioning it without asking for it. Mentioning
can occur before it's right to be before it's appropriate to be
asking. במקום ששואל אינו דין שיזכיר, bimkom shesho'el eino din sheyazkir, if
you're still in a period of asking for it, it's over פסח
Pesach and you think you're still asking for it over פסח, Pesach,
then obviously you should still be saying it. How could you be
asking for it and not saying it? אלא אמר עולא, ela amar
Ula, so עולא Ula said no, תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי יהודה, trei
tanna'ei aliba deRabbi Yehuda, easy is the answer, there's a debate of
תנאים tanna'im what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said. Our משנה Mishnah assumes
he says you stop saying משיב הרוח Mashiv Haruach on the first
day of פסח Pesach and therefore you would also stop saying תן
טל ומטר Ten Tal uMatar because if you're not saying משיב הרוח
Mashiv Haruach you're not saying תן טל ומטר. Ten Tal uMatar. And
the other תנא tanna says no, you say both of them until
the end of פסח. Pesach. Okay? That's the easiest answer. It's a
debate, you know, it's two versions of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now
we're going to try to get more creative answers to reconcile it
and have them both actually be saying the same thing. So let's
take a look. רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says, מאי עד שיעבור הפסח? mai ad sheya'avor haPesach? What does
it mean that you say, you know, תן טל ומטר Ten Tal
uMatar until פסח Pesach is done, even though we're saying that according
to our תנא tanna you would only say it till the first
day? עד שיעבור שליח ציבור ראשון היורד ביום טוב ראשון של פסח.
ad sheya'avor sheliach tzibur rishon hayored beyom tov rishon shel Pesach. That's
a very creative re-read. It doesn't mean until פסח Pesach has passed
over, again I don't mean to be making a pun anymore but
okay, it doesn't mean until פסח Pesach has passed, it means until
the שליח ציבור sheliach tzibur passes in front of the congregation on
the first day of פסח. Pesach. So עד שיעבור הפסח ad sheya'avor
haPesach means until the first day of פסח. Pesach. All right? So
that's a very creative re-read, but even with that re-read the גמרא
Gemara doesn't buy it. עד מוסף. ad musaf. עד מוסף. ad musaf.
אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so אביי Abaye said one minute,
you can't say you say תן טל ומטר Ten Tal uMatar until
מוסף Musaf of the first day of פסח. Pesach. Because when do
you really stop saying תן טל ומטר? Ten Tal uMatar? מנחה Mincha
before. Once it's יום טוב Yom Tov you don't have the ברכה,
bracha, you don't have ברכנו את השנה הזאת, barechenu et hashana hazot,
right? So how so, so אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so
אביי Abaye said, שאלה ביום טוב מי איכא? she'ela beyom tov mi
ika? You don't have asking for it on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
What do you mean you say you ask for it until the,
you know, until מוסף Musaf or until, you know, the davenning on
the first day of יום טוב? Yom Tov? אמר ליה אין, amar
leh in, yes. שאלה דמתורגמן. she'ela demeturgeman. The translator can ask. Now
that's a bizarre thing. What translator? So רש״י Rashi says, was there
a translator of the davenning? Was it a translator of the קריאת
התורה? kri'at haTorah? So if you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi
says where it says מתורגמן, meturgeman, I'm trying to find the רש״י.
Rashi.
Yeah. רש״י Rashi says דמתורגמן, demeturgeman, well actually let's first read the
line in the גמרא. Gemara. וכי מתורגמן שואל דבר שאינו צריך לציבור?
vechi meturgeman sho'el davar she'eino tzarich latzibur?
I'm sorry, no, I was right. The first רש״י Rashi says אין
שאלה דמתורגמן. in she'ela demeturgeman. רש״י Rashi says בדרשה bedrasha about ten
lines before the lines are
wide. שבדרשה שהוא דורש אומר ברכת שאלה לבדה. shebedrasha shehu doresh omer
birkat she'ela levada. A bizarre type of idea. First of all the
מתורגמן meturgeman now here is like the guy giving the sermon. I
don't know why he's called a מתורגמן, meturgeman, maybe the person who
would translate the קריאת התורה kri'at haTorah would also interrupt and give
a little דרשה drasha somewhere at some point and inserting in your
sermon maybe you'll say a ברכה bracha of, you know, on יום
טוב Yom Tov of תן טל ומטר לברכה. Ten Tal uMatar livracha.
Like where, who's making this stuff up? So anyway, so that's what
says that you would say until, until davenning on the first day
of
יום טוב. Yom Tov. until when is the rain needed? But anyway,
clearly we're not going to buy into this idea that there would
be some mention of ותן טל ומטר לברכה Vesein Tal Umattar Livracha
on the first day outside the context of דאווענינג. davening. So that's
not a legitimate re-read of that משנה mishna that you ask ותן
טל ומטר Vesein Tal Umattar until the first day דאווענינג davening because
you stop asking for it earlier. אלא מחוורתא כדעולא, Ela mivarta k'de'Ulla,
it's better like עולא. Ulla. Fine, let's just accept that it's a
מחלוקת machlokes of רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda position. But now we're going
to have— we're not giving up. רבא אמר, Raba amar, רבא Rava
says another way of reconciling the two משניות. mishnayos. מאי עד שיעבור
הפסח, Mai ad she-ya'avor ha-Pesach, what does it mean until פסח Pesach
has passed? עד שיעבור זמן שחיטת הפסח. Ad she-ya'avor zman shechitas ha-Pesach.
So פסח Pesach doesn't mean חג המצות, Chag HaMatzos, פסח Pesach means
what it means more biblically. It means the bring of the קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. And it means until the time of the שחיטה
shechita of the פסח Pesach has passed over. ותחילתו כסופו, U-techilaso k'sofo,
like the beginning, so is the end. מה תחילתו מזכיר אף על
פי שאינו שואל, Ma techilaso mazkir af al pi she-eino sho'el,
the same way at the beginning of the process, you start mentioning
משיב הרוח mashiv haruach before you start asking, at least until חשון.
Cheshvan. אף סופו, Af sofo, even at the end of the process,
אף על פי שאינו שואל, af al pi she-eino sho'el, you stop
asking according to him. Now, I don't get why it means the
time of שחיטה shechting the פסח Pesach has passed, because שחיטה shechting
the פסח Pesach is the whole afternoon. רש"י Rashi says it means
after the morning has passed. But anyway, that is the time of
שחיטה shechting the פסח Pesach anyway. But okay. So in the afternoon
at מנחה mincha time, אף על פי שאינו שואל, af al pi
she-eino sho'el, you're no longer asking. Nevertheless, you're still mentioning. So the
mentioning of it— you jump in, begin early and continue later, but
the explicit asking does not, you know, is at a smaller period
of time. So עד שיעבור הפסח ad she-ya'avor ha-Pesach and the next
משנה mishna means that you stop saying— you stop saying משיב הרוח
mashiv haruach by מוסף musaf of פסח Pesach of the first day,
and you stop saying ותן טל ומטר Vesein Tal Umattar by ערב
פסח erev Pesach or by מנחה mincha of ערב פסח. erev Pesach.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back, okay,
so logically that makes sense. It's a little difficult read of עד
שיעבור הפסח. ad she-ya'avor ha-Pesach. But בשלמא, bishlama, he says I don't
understand the— you know, even— I don't really get the logic just
because you've created this parallel. בשלמא תחילתו מזכיר, Bishlama techilaso mazkir,
I get that you could start mentioning it at the beginning, משיב
הרוח mashiv haruach before you start asking. הזכרה נמי ריצוי שאלה היא,
Hazkara nami ritzui she'eila hi, and this is exactly the issue we've
been discussing. How much is משיב הרוח, mashiv haruach, you know, a
lead-in to saying ותן טל ומטר Vesein Tal Umattar or is it
independent in terms of its function in שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So
he says, look, he's taking the approach that— that— that משיב הרוח
mashiv haruach is a ריצוי שאלה היא. ritzui she'eila hi. It is
a— it is like a— appeasing, you know, laying the groundwork for
making the request. First you praise God, when it's the right time
about this— about this capacity, this power, and then you start asking
God to act on it. Okay, so I get why it precedes.
אלא סופו, Ela sofo, but at the end, מאי ריצוי שאלה איכא,
mai ritzui she'eila ika, right? If you're done asking for rain, why
would you keep on mentioning it? The whole idea is to mention
it as a lead-in to ask. When the asking is done, the
mentioning should be done. Again, this gets to the heart of the
question of whether you see משיב הרוח mashiv haruach just in this
capacity or not. But אביי Abaye sees it just in that capacity,
so he can't accept that you continue to say משיב הרוח mashiv
haruach after you're done asking. אלא מחוורתא כדעולא, Ela mivarta k'de'Ulla, once
again, we reject these ways of reconciling and we go back to
עולא Ulla saying it's two opinions. But what this גמרא Gemara has
done is it's again brought this issue of the relationship of, you
know, משיב הרוח mashiv haruach to ותן טל ומטר. Vesein Tal Umattar.
That on the one hand, we've accepted the idea that you could
start saying משיב הרוח mashiv haruach a good deal before you say
ותן טל ומטר. Vesein Tal Umattar. Certainly that's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer
position. You say it in— you say משיב הרוח mashiv haruach in
סוכות, Succos, you only ask for it after. But even רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua could have saying it the whole duration until
מרחשון Marcheshvan and only start asking in מרחשון. Marcheshvan. And then we
ask at the end, because there seemed to be a contradiction of
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda about when you end. And the גמרא Gemara
was exploring the possibility that they would diverge there as well. But
there the גמרא Gemara says no, it says there it doesn't make
sense. It makes sense that משיב הרוח mashiv haruach can come before,
you know, at— ותן טל ומטר, Vesein Tal Umattar, but you can't
be on the one hand— the first suggestion was rejected. You can't
be saying ותן טל ומטר Vesein Tal Umattar without saying משיב הרוח,
mashiv haruach, that would make no sense. And you can't even, according
to אביי, Abaye, continue saying משיב הרוח mashiv haruach after you've stopped
asking. There would be no point, says אביי, Abaye, to continue saying
it. Now, that's not as logically impossible, that has to do with
the function of משיב הרוח, mashiv haruach, but at least אביי Abaye
says there would be no point to continue saying it if you
were no longer asking for rain, no longer interested in the— in
God bringing the rain.
Okay, yeah, isn't— isn't ריצוי ritzui a technical term we saw with
the קרבנות korbanos from עבודה, avoda, like— use of ריצוי? ritzui?
Well, it says, you know, because that's very common in the פסוקים,
psukim, you know, יהי רצון לפניך... yehi ratzon lefanecha... המקריב אותו לא,
hamakriv oto lo,
no, that's not ירצה, yeiratzeh, that's לא יחשב, lo yechashev, but לרצון
לפני השם, l’ratzon lifnei Hashem, you know, ריצוי ritzui
is a common word used in the פסוקים pesukim by the קרבנות
korbanot to mean that the קרבן korban is accepted. And here, you’re
right, it’s the same term that’s now being applied to תפילה. tefillah.
Yeah, so that’s intentional.
Right, you are correct.
It’s a good question when how much ריצוי ritzui gets used by,
you know, מרצה אינו מרצה, meratzeh eino meratzeh, whatever the very, very
common not only in the פסוקים pesukim but in the technical halachic
language of קרבנות, korbanot, I’d have to think about how much it
gets used by תפילה.
tefillah. This idea of rain in its time coming as a divine
acknowledgement of appropriate moral behavior, let’s say, or religious behavior of humanity.
Right, right, although I guess again I don’t know if, yes, although
I do think it’s like an interesting question of the use of
קרבנות korbanot terminology by תפילה tefillah in general.
תפילת קרבן נחשון.
tefillat
korban nachshon.
Right, ויהי לזכרון. v’yehi l’zikaron.
Right, right, right.
But we’re still tied back on some level to the water libation.
Yes, which is בא לרצות על המים, ba l’ratzot al hamayim, which
is correct. And that’s, you know, and it’s a very good point.
I mean, רבי אליעזר’s Rabbi Eliezer’s language quoted in the ברייתא baraita
on דף ס"ז daf samach zayin was ארבעה מינים הללו, arba’ah minim
hallalu, I think there he used explicitly, אלו ארבעה מינים הללו אינם
באים אלא לרצות על המים. elu arba’ah minim hallalu einam ba’im ela
l’ratzot al hamayim. And that was, and that’s a very good point
because that is exactly the point that the ריצוי ritzui can come
before the בקשה, bakasha, the sort of getting God, you know, to
sort of doing an offering and doing something that God will make
God desirous without and, you know, without yet asking for it and
without it yet being the time. And here too, the idea is
it’s a ריצוי ritzui for the ultimate בקשה. bakasha. So that’s a
very good point. Okay, so now we’ve got that issue about the
relationship of the two, but we’re not done. So let’s take a
look. אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi
Yochanan, says רב אסי Rav Assi in the name of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, we’re about eight lines down by the asterisk and wide
lines. הלכה כרבי יהודה, halacha k’Rabbi Yehuda, we rule like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, and that we know we do that. We know that
we switch off at מוסף musaf on סוכות Sukkot and פסח. Pesach.
So אמר ליה רב זירא לרב אסי, amar leh Rav Zeira l’Rav
Assi, so רב זירא Rav Zeira said to רב אסי Rav Assi
who quoted רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in terms of this פסק, psak,
ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי, u’mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi, did רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say that? והתנן, vehatnan, but we’ve taught in
the משנה, mishnah, בשלושה במרחשוון שואלין את הגשמים, b’shlosha b’marcheshvan shoalin et
hageshamim, you start asking on the third of מרחשוון. Marcheshvan. רבן גמליאל
אומר בשבעה בו, Rabban Gamliel omer b’shiva bo, on the seventh. ואמר
רבי אלעזר הלכה כרבן גמליאל, v’amar Rabbi Elazar halacha k’Rabban Gamliel, we
rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and we start saying ותן טל
ומטר v’tein tal u’matar on the seventh of מרחשוון Marcheshvan in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So why is this a problem? So רב אסי
Rav Assi is assuming, think again, what we sort of have now
been assuming the opposite, but he’s assuming that saying ותן טל ומטר
v’tein tal u’matar is co-extensive with משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם. mashiv haruach
u’morid hageshem. So how can you say we rule like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that we do the switch off on שמיני עצרת? Shemini
Atzeret? It’s not true. We only start saying ותן טל ומטר v’tein
tal u’matar on מרחשוון, Marcheshvan, seventh of מרחשוון, Marcheshvan, and he assumes
that ותן טל ומטר v’tein tal u’matar is the same as משיב
הרוח. mashiv haruach. So either they should both be שמיני עצרת Shemini
Atzeret or the day after שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, or they should
both be ז' מרחשוון. zayin Marcheshvan. So it can't be that we
rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because we rule ז' מרחשוון zayin
Marcheshvan for ותן טל ומטר. v’tein tal u’matar.
I thought the question was did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say.
Well, that’s going to be one of the
answers. אמר ליה גברא אגברא קא רמית, amar leh gabra a’gabra ka
ramit, what are you bothering me with this? That’s one of them
is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and the other is רבי אלעזר. Rabbi
Elazar. Okay, but the more interesting answer is that why are you
assuming that ותן טל ומטר v’tein tal u’matar is the same as
משיב הרוח? mashiv haruach? ואיבעית אימא, v’iba’it eima, and if you want
I could say, לא קשיא, lo kashya, כאן לשאול כאן להזכיר, kan
l’sha’ol kan l’hazkir, exactly the difference that we’ve been talking about, that
even within a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and a רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua approach, they accept that there’s a difference between saying להזכיר, l’hazkir,
משיב הרוח, mashiv haruach, that can begin on שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret,
and ותן טל ומטר, v’tein tal u’matar, which begins only on ז'
מרחשוון. zayin Marcheshvan. So the גמרא gemara says, one minute, that’s not
an answer. To say it’s not רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is one
thing, but to say that there’s a difference between the two, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan rejects the idea that there’s a difference between the
two. והאמר רבי יוחנן, veha’amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says,
במקום ששואל מזכיר, b’makom shesho’el mazkir,
as long as, wherever you’re asking, you’re mentioning. Now, if anybody remembers
their, you know, prepositional logic from high school, just because if P
then Q doesn’t mean, right, if Q then P. Just because every
time you say ותן טל ומטר v’tein tal u’matar you’re saying משיב
הרוח mashiv haruach does not mean that whenever you’re saying משיב הרוח
mashiv haruach you’re saying ותן טל ומטר. v’tein tal u’matar. Okay, but
the גמרא gemara is assuming that, and it’s assuming for רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan they’re completely co-extensive. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says, so
its first answer is exactly not this. ההיא להפסקה, hahi l’hafskah, that’s
when it comes to ending, like we said, right? So if you’ve
got, let me visualize this a little bit, right? If you’ve got
here שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, right, and then let’s say here becomes,
like this is all תשרי, Tishrei, right, and then this is חשוון,
Cheshvan, the מרחשוון, Marcheshvan, and then you have שבעה מרחשוון shiva Marcheshvan
here, right, so here what you’ve got is you’ve got, right, so
if you’ve got basically that you’re saying here, you know, להזכיר, l’hazkir,
you’re saying
משיב הרוח, mashiv haruach, right? And then you start saying here, right
you start saying ותן טל ומטר *ve-ten tal u-matar*. And then you
get to, you get to,
what do you get to? You get to ט"ו ניסן *Tu B'Nisan*,
right? You get to פסח *Pesach*. You get to the wall. And
then you stop saying it. Okay. So he says, yes, במקום ששואל
מזכיר *be-makom she-sho'el mazkir*,
as long as you're asking you're mentioning, that's when it comes to
ending. So it means when you stop asking you don't continue saying,
which is a suggestion the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has. Maybe even you
stopped asking, maybe you should continue saying משיב הרוח Mashiv Haruach? *Mashiv
HaRuach* even after you're done asking. No. Once you no longer want
it, once it's not a lead-in, right here it's a lead-in, a,
you know, ריצוי שאלה *ritztui she'elah*, a lead-in to begin asking. And
as long as you ask you mention, when you stop asking you
stop mentioning. There's no idea of continuing and that's what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said before. That's להפסיק *le-hafsik*. But to begin, you could
begin one before the other. The גמרא *Gemara* says, ההוא לפסוקי איתמר
*Hahu le-fiskuy itamar*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says wait, we have another statement of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* which really says they're co-extensive at both sides.
ואמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan*, התחיל להזכיר מתחיל לשאול
*hitchil lehazkir matchil lisho'el*, as soon as you stop start
mentioning משיב הרוח Mashiv Haruach *Mashiv HaRuach* you start asking, that's explicit
that they start at the same time. פוסק מלשאול פוסק מלהזכיר *posek
milisho'el posek mile-hazkir*, when you stop asking you stop mentioning. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, he has this bizarre idea that we
thought was, you know, bizarre, that the גמרא *Gemara* assumed that they
were completely the same time, this is actually we find out a
position of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says משיב
הרוח Mashiv Haruach, *Mashiv HaRuach* and ותן טל ומטר *ve-ten tal u-matar*
all occurred exactly at the same time. So how could רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* say that and say we rule like רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*? If he's saying we rule like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* it
means that we start saying ותן טל ומטר *ve-ten tal u-matar* day
after שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres. *Shemini Atzeret* because he says ותן טל
ומטר *ve-ten tal u-matar* follows exactly with משיב הרוח Mashiv Haruach *Mashiv
HaRuach*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אלא לא קשיא הא לן והא
להו *Ela lo kashya ha lan ve-ha lehu*, this is for them
this is for this is for us this is for them. So
meaning for us, we would start saying, we would start
saying, excuse me,
we would start saying ותן טל ומטר *ve-ten tal u-matar* only on
ז' מרחשון Zayin Mar-Cheshvan? *Zayin Marcheshvan*. Very bizarre, the משנה *Mishnah* written
in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* that says ז' מרחשון *Zayin Marcheshvan* is
talking about בבל *Bavel*. Okay, we would start saying that only in
בבל *Bavel*. We would wait in בבל *Bavel*. No, no, no, no.
There there would presumably be a break, maybe, I don't know. Maybe
you're right. Maybe we'd start both of them, but that would be
ז' מרחשון *Zayin Marcheshvan* and that's for בבל *Bavel*, that's that that
משנה *Mishnah*. And the idea of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, that's ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. There we need the rain earlier. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, one minute, מאי שנא לדידן *mai shna l'didan*? How is
it different for us? דאית לן פירי בדברא *de-it lan pirei be-dabra*,
we still have our crops out in the field and we don't
want it to rain, you know, at we want it until later.
We don't want rain in תשרי *Tishrei*, we only want it to
begin raining in חשון *Cheshvan*. So that's why you say for us
we'll wait till ז' *Zayin*. לדידהו נמי אית להו עולי רגלים *l'didehu
nami it lehu olei regalim*. You know, the משנה *Mishnah* says the
reason that you wanted to wait till מרחשון *Marcheshvan* is you wanted
to wait for the people who came up for the רגל *Regel*
to get home, so they should also be waiting. Now there's an
obvious answer, right? We're talking about nowadays. So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
no. כי קאמר רבי יהודה בזמן שאין בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, קיים
*Ki ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda bizman she-ein Beit HaMikdash kayam*. He's talking when
there's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*. So therefore in ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* they're happy to have the rain right after סוכות
Succos, *Sukkot* and that's when he means we פסקן *pasken* like רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. And in בבל *Bavel* we'll wait till מרחשון *Marcheshvan*
for the rain and that's the פסק psak. *psak* of the next
משנה *Mishnah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, השתא דאתית להכי *hashta de-atit
le-hachi*, now that you've come along to this distinction of whether there's
a בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, הא והא לדידהו *ha ve-ha l'didehu*, it
could all work for ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, which is good 'cause
we're talking about Tannaic sources, so why should it be about בבל
*Bavel*? ולא קשיא כאן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים כאן בזמן שאין בית
המקדש קיים *ve-lo kashya kan bizman she-Beit HaMikdash kayam kan bizman she-ein
Beit HaMikdash kayam*. That the משנה *Mishnah* that we say we פסקן
*pasken* like that you wait until ז' מרחשון *Zayin Marcheshvan*, that's when
there's a בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, you have to wait for the
עולי רגלים *olei regalim* to get home. The idea that we פסקן
*pasken* like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, and again assuming להזכיר *lehazkir* and
לשאול *lisho'el* are the same thing, that's for nowadays. Nowadays we can
get the rain right after סוכות Succos, *Sukkot*. So now the גמרא
*Gemara* ends, ואנן דאית לן *ve-anan de-it lan* תרי יומי *trei yomei*,
for us that we hold two days of, so that of שמיני
עצרת Shemini Atzeres, *Shemini Atzeret*, right? שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres. *Shemini Atzeret*
and שמחת תורה Simchas Torah, *Simchat Torah*. When do we do the
transition? You know, 'cause which day is the real שמיני עצרת Shemini
Atzeres. *Shemini Atzeret*? היכי עבדינן *heichi avdinan*, what do you do? So
אמר רב מתחיל במוספין ופוסק במנחה ערבית ושחרית וחוזר במוספין *Amar Rav
matchil be-musafin u-posek be-mincha arvit ve-shacharit ve-chozer be-musafin*.
So you do it on מוסף Musaf שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres. *Musaf
Shemini Atzeret*, then because you have to do it on the second
day too at מוסף Musaf, *Musaf*, so you have to go back
to the normal thing after מוסף *Musaf* and stop and you know
and stop saying it and then begin saying it again in מוסף
*Musaf* on שמחת תורה Simchas Torah *Simchat Torah*. So אמר להו שמואל
Shmuel *amar lehu Shmuel*, so שמואל *Shmuel* says to them, פוקו ואמרו
ליה לאבא *puku ve-imru leh le-Abba*,
or he said to his students go tell אבא *Abba*, which is
his way of referring respectfully to רב *Rav*, אחר שעשיתו קודש *achar
she-asito kodesh*, once you said it מוסף *Musaf* of שמיני *Shemini*. As
you've indicated that today is שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres, not that it
might be the seventh
day. So תעשהו חול, taseihu chol, you're going to go back and
not say משיב הרוח? Mashiv Haruach By not saying it, you're saying
it's still סוכות, Succos, it's not necessarily שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres, Once
you say משיב הרוח in שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres you're indicating it's
no longer סוכות, it really is שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres So you
can't go back now and not say it, which would indicate it's
not שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres אלא אמר שמואל, Ella amar Shmuel, rather
שמואל says, מתחיל במוספין ובמנחה, mas'chil be-musafim u-ve-mincha, once you do it
at מוסף you do it at מנחה Mincha because you have to
end the day signifying that you're treating it as שמיני עצרת. ופוסק
ערבית ושחרית, U-posek arvis ve-shacharis, but then when it comes שמחת תורה,
then it's a new day, now we should go back to pretending
that today might be שמיני עצרת, and if today שמחת תורה was
שמיני עצרת, we wouldn't be saying it מעריב Maariv and שחרית. Shacharis.
וחוזר ומתחיל במוספין, Ve-chozer u-mas'chil be-musafim, and you go back and then
you start saying it at מוסף, so you've to replay the day
when it gets to be the next day. ורבא אמר, Ve-Rava amar,
כיון שהתחיל שוב אין פוסק, keivan she-hischil shuv ein posek, which is
obviously what we do. Excuse me, once you start saying משיב הרוח,
you've indicated that now is the time for משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
Mashiv Haruach u-morid ha-geshem and from שמיני עצרת on you're not going
to change, which is clearly our פסק. But just to go back
and say that the גמרא ended up with a with a position
of רבי יוחנן which we had been avoiding, but it clearly is
רבי יוחנן's position, which is, which is that משיב הרוח is exactly
coextensive with ותן טל ומטר לברכה. ten tal u-mator livracha. And then
it becomes the question, do you start saying both of them on
שמיני עצרת or the day after סוכות, and you start asking, or
do you start waiting for both of them until ז' מרחשון? And
that would then sort of... גמרא says well maybe it makes a
difference time of the בית המקדש, not the time of the בית
המקדש. But for us what's conceptually interesting is that the whole earlier
part of the דף daf had worked to separate those two and
that obviously is the way we פוסקין, pasken, we פוסקין pasken that
you say משיב הרוח from שמיני עצרת and you ask only in
ז' חשון, Zayin Cheshvan, but we have a רבי יוחנן position that
really brings the two of them together.